I'm going to speak to you about the global refugee crisis
今天談的是全球難民危機的問題。
and my aim is to show you that this crisis
我想讓各位知道，
but also show you that this is as much about us and who we are
也讓各位知道這關乎我們， 以及我們是誰。
as it is a trial of the refugees on the front line.
這是對於前線難民的試驗。
For me, this is not just a professional obligation,
對我來說，這不只是種職業義務，
because I run an NGO supporting refugees and displaced people around the world.
只因我在非營利機構支援， 並安置在世界各處的難民。
It's personal.
這與個人切身相關。
I love this picture.
我很愛這張照片。
That really handsome guy on the right,
右邊那個很帥的男生，
that's not me.
不是我。
That's my dad, Ralph, in London, in 1940
那是我父親雷夫， 1940 年在倫敦拍的。
with his father Samuel.
旁邊是他父親撒姆爾。
They were Jewish refugees from Belgium.
他們是比利時的猶太難民，
They fled the day the Nazis invaded.
在納粹入侵當天逃走。
And I love this picture, too.
我也很愛這張照片。
It's a group of refugee children
這是一群難民孩子，
arriving in England in 1946 from Poland.
1946 年從波蘭遷到英國。
And in the middle is my mother, Marion.
中間那位是我母親瑪麗安，
She was sent to start a new life
為了有新人生，她被送走，
in a new country
到了一個新國家，
on her own
而且是獨自一人，
at the age of 12.
在 12 歲時。
I know this:
我知道
if Britain had not admitted refugees
要是英國在 1940 年代
in the 1940s,
拒絕難民，
I certainly would not be here today.
我今天就不會站在這裡了。
Yet 70 years on, the wheel has come full circle.
但 70 年後，時代巨輪轉了回來，
The sound is of walls being built,
那些築起高牆的聲音、
vengeful political rhetoric,
充滿報復性的政治語言，
humanitarian values and principles on fire
受到挑戰的人道價值觀以及原則，
in the very countries that 70 years ago said never again
出現在 70 年前
Last year, every minute,
去年的每一分鐘，
24 more people were displaced from their homes
至少有 24 人
another chemical weapon attack in Syria,
敘利亞發生另一起化武攻擊、
the Taliban on the rampage in Afghanistan,
塔利班在阿富汗橫行、
girls driven from their school in northeast Nigeria by Boko Haram.
奈及利亞東北部的激進組織 「博科聖地」將女孩逐出學校。
These are not people moving to another country
這些人移到另一個城市
to get a better life.
不是為了過更好的生活，
They're fleeing for their lives.
而是為了活命。
It's a real tragedy
這是真正的悲劇。
that the world's most famous refugee can't come to speak to you here today.
世上最有名的難民 今天無法在這和你們對話。
Many of you will know this picture.
你們大多看過這張照片。
It shows the lifeless body
這是具無生命的身體，
of five-year-old Alan Kurdi,
是五歲的艾倫．庫爾迪，
a Syrian refugee who died in the Mediterranean in 2015.
一名 2015 年死於 地中海的敘利亞難民，
He died alongside 3,700 others trying to get to Europe.
身邊還有 3700 名難民 試圖逃到歐洲。
The next year, 2016,
隔年，2016 年，
5,000 people died.
5000 人死亡。
It's too late for them,
對他們來說一切都太遲了，
but it's not too late for millions of others.
但對其他數以百萬的難民還不遲。
It's not too late for people like Frederick.
對像費得列克 這樣的人來說還不算晚。
I met him in the Nyarugusu refugee camp in Tanzania.
我在坦尚尼亞的 尼亞魯古蘇難民營認識他。
He's from Burundi.
他從蒲隆地來，
He wanted to know where could he complete his studies.
想知道自己可以在哪裡完成學業。
He'd done 11 years of schooling. He wanted a 12th year.
他已經讀了十一年的書， 也想繼續讀下去。
He said to me, "I pray that my days do not end here
他告訴我：「我向神呼求， 我不想死在這裡，
in this refugee camp."
死在這個難民營。」
And it's not too late for Halud.
對哈魯德來說也不算遲。
Her parents were Palestinian refugees
她的父母是巴勒斯坦難民，
living in the Yarmouk refugee camp outside Damascus.
住在大馬士革外的雅爾矛克難民營。
She was born to refugee parents,
她是難民的孩子，
and now she's a refugee herself in Lebanon.
如今也成為黎巴嫩的難民。
She's working for the International Rescue Committee to help other refugees,
她在國際救援委員會 幫忙其他難民，
but she has no certainty at all
但對於自己的未來，
about her future,
她沒有任何把握，
where it is or what it holds.
像是未來在哪裡，或未來有什麼。
This talk is about Frederick, about Halud
這場演講是關於費得列克， 關於哈魯德，
and about millions like them:
以及無數名和他們一樣的難民：
why they're displaced,
關於他們為何遷移、
how they survive, what help they need and what our responsibilities are.
如何生存、需要什麼幫助， 以及我們的責任。
I truly believe this,
我真心認為，
that the biggest question in the 21st century
21 世紀最大的問題
concerns our duty to strangers.
在於我們對陌生人的責任。
The future "you" is about your duties
未來的「你們」，是關乎
You know better than anyone,
各位比其他人更清楚，
the world is more connected than ever before,
這個世界的連結比從前緊密得多，
yet the great danger
但更大的危機在於
is that we're consumed by our divisions.
我們都被分歧這事消耗掉了。
And there is no better test of that
從我們對待難民的態度
than how we treat refugees.
最能看出問題所在。
Here are the facts: 65 million people
事實是，去年有六千五百萬人
displaced from their homes by violence and persecution last year.
因為暴力及迫害被迫離開家，
If it was a country,
假如這些人組成一個國家，
that would be the 21st largest country in the world.
將會是 21 世紀世界最大的國家。
Most of those people, about 40 million, stay within their own home country,
這群人中，約四千萬人待在祖國，
but 25 million are refugees.
但其中二千五百萬名是難民。
That means they cross a border into a neighboring state.
這表示他們跨越國界到鄰國。
Most of them are living in poor countries,
他們大多住在貧困國家，
relatively poor or lower-middle-income countries, like Lebanon,
相對貧困或中低收入國家， 例如黎巴嫩，
where Halud is living.
哈魯德的居住地。
In Lebanon, one in four people is a refugee,
在黎巴嫩， 每四人就有一人是難民，
a quarter of the whole population.
是全數人口的四分之一。
And refugees stay for a long time.
而且難民會待很長的時間。
The average length of displacement
他們流離失所的平均時間
is 10 years.
是 10 年。
I went to what was the world's largest refugee camp, in eastern Kenya.
我去過肯亞東部世界最大的難民營，
It's called Dadaab.
它叫達達布，
It was built in 1991-92
在 1991 到 1992 間成立，
as a "temporary camp" for Somalis fleeing the civil war.
作為索馬利亞人 逃離內戰的「短暫營區」。
I met Silo.
我遇見西蘿，
And naïvely I said to Silo,
並且很天真地問她：
"Do you think you'll ever go home to Somalia?"
「妳覺得自己可能回到 索馬利亞的家嗎？」
And she said, "What do you mean, go home?
她說：「你說回家是什麼意思？
I was born here."
我就是在這裡出生的。」
And then when I asked the camp management
然後我問營區的管理員，
how many of the 330,000 people in that camp were born there,
33 萬人中有多少人 是在那裡出生的。
they gave me the answer:
他們的答案是
100,000.
10 萬。
That's what long-term displacement means.
這是長期流離失所真正的意思。
Now, the causes of this are deep:
注意，這個現象的成因很深層：
weak states that can't support their own people,
較弱勢的國家無法支持人民、
an international political system
國際政治系統
weaker than at any time since 1945
也處於 1945 年以來最糟的狀況，
and differences over theology, governance, engagement with the outside world
加上穆斯林世界主要地區的
Now, those are long-term, generational challenges.
這些都是長期且普遍的挑戰。
That's why I say that this refugee crisis is a trend and not a blip.
所以我認為難民危機是種趨勢， 而非暫時性變動。
And it's complex, and when you have big, large, long-term, complex problems,
而當人們遇到龐大、長期 且複雜的問題時，
people think nothing can be done.
就會認為無計可施了。
When Pope Francis went to Lampedusa,
教宗方濟各到蘭佩杜薩島時，
off the coast of Italy, in 2014,
2014 年在義大利海岸邊
he accused all of us and the global population
控訴我們和全球人民
of what he called "the globalization of indifference."
犯了他所謂「冷漠全球化」的罪。
It's a haunting phrase.
這是個讓人難以忘記的詞。
It means that our hearts have turned to stone.
意思是我們的心已經變為石頭了。
Now, I don't know, you tell me.
我也不知道，請告訴我，
Are you allowed to argue with the Pope, even at a TED conference?
你們能和教宗爭論嗎， 甚至是在 TED 會議中？
But I think it's not right.
但我覺得他錯了。
I think people do want to make a difference,
我認為人們想要改變，
but they just don't know whether there are any solutions to this crisis.
只是不知道有什麼辦法可以解決。
And what I want to tell you today
而我今天要告訴各位的，
is that though the problems are real, the solutions are real, too.
就是問題很真實， 但解決方法也很實際。
Solution one:
方法一：
these refugees need to get into work in the countries where they're living,
這些難民必須在居住地找到工作，
and the countries where they're living need massive economic support.
而這些國家需要龐大的經濟支援。
In Uganda in 2014, they did a study:
2014 年烏干達有份研究顯示：
80 percent of refugees in the capital city Kampala
首都康培拉的難民有八成
needed no humanitarian aid because they were working.
因為有工作而不需要人道協助。
They were supported into work.
他們受到支持而能工作。
Solution number two:
解決方案二：
education for kids is a lifeline, not a luxury,
孩童教育是條救命線， 而非一種奢侈，
when you're displaced for so long.
尤其是被迫離鄉這麼久。
Kids can bounce back when they're given the proper social, emotional support
有適當的社會、情感支援， 孩童就能重新振作，
alongside literacy and numeracy.
同時具有識字力及計算能力。
I've seen it for myself.
我曾親眼見識過。
But half of the world's refugee children of primary school age
但世上有一半 已經該上小學的難民孩童
get no education at all,
完全沒受任何教育；
and three-quarters of secondary school age get no education at all.
而該上中學的孩子 有四分之三也沒受任何教育。
That's crazy.
這太誇張了。
Solution number three:
解決方案三：
most refugees are in urban areas, in cities, not in camps.
多數難民都住在都會或城市， 而非難民營。
What would you or I want if we were a refugee in a city?
若我們是城市的難民， 你我會想要什麼？
We would want money to pay rent or buy clothes.
我們會需要錢來付租金或買衣服。
That is the future of the humanitarian system,
這正是未來人道系統該做的，
or a significant part of it:
或至少是其中很重要的一部分：
give people cash so that you boost the power of refugees
給人們現金，提升難民的能力，
and you'll help the local economy.
同時也會促進當地經濟。
And there's a fourth solution, too,
還有第四個方法。
that's controversial but needs to be talked about.
有點爭議，但仍需要提出來討論。
The most vulnerable refugees need to be given a new start
最脆弱的難民需要在新的國家
and a new life in a new country,
有個新的開始，新的人生。
including in the West.
包括在西方世界。
The numbers are relatively small, hundreds of thousands, not millions,
這些難民數量相對較少， 大概數十萬人，
but the symbolism is huge.
但有龐大的象徵意義。
Now is not the time to be banning refugees,
現在不是禁止難民的時候，
as the Trump administration proposes.
就像川普政府提議的那樣。
It's a time to be embracing people who are victims of terror.
是時候去擁抱那些 身受恐懼所苦的人了。
And remember --
請記得……
(Applause)
（掌聲）
Remember, anyone who asks you, "Are they properly vetted?"
記得，如果有人問你： 「他們受過調查了嗎？」
that's a really sensible and good question to ask.
這是合情理的好問題。
The truth is, refugees arriving for resettlement
真相是，要定居的難民
are more vetted than any other population arriving in our countries.
比其他人口受到更多的審查。
So while it's reasonable to ask the question,
所以儘管這個問題很合理，
it's not reasonable to say that refugee is another word for terrorist.
但說難民等於恐怖分子卻很不合理。
Now, what happens --
好，那……
(Applause)
（掌聲）
What happens when refugees can't get work,
當這些難民找不到工作、
they can't get their kids into school,
無法讓孩子們就學、
they can't get cash, they can't get a legal route to hope?
沒有錢，也不能指望 合法管道求生，怎麼辦？
What happens is they take risky journeys.
結果就是他們 選擇走風險較大的途徑。
I went to Lesbos, this beautiful Greek island, two years ago.
兩年前我到過美麗的 希臘列斯伏斯島，
It's a home to 90,000 people.
那裡有 9 萬人。
In one year, 500,000 refugees went across the island.
一年內，50 萬名難民 途經這座島嶼。
And I want to show you what I saw
我想讓你們看看 當時我所看到的景象。
when I drove across to the north of the island:
當時我正要開往島嶼北部，
a pile of life jackets of those who had made it to shore.
那裡堆滿了 平安抵達岸上者的救生衣。
And when I looked closer,
而當我看得更仔細時，
there were small life jackets for children,
發現當中有給孩童的小救生衣，
yellow ones.
黃色的。
And I took this picture.
我拍了這張照片。
You probably can't see the writing, but I want to read it for you.
你可能看不到上頭的字， 但我想讀給你聽：
"Warning: will not protect against drowning."
「警告：無法保證不溺水。」
So in the 21st century,
所以在 21 世紀，
children are being given life jackets
孩童有救生衣
to reach safety in Europe
可以安全抵達歐洲，
even though those jackets will not save their lives
即使那些救生衣無法在 他們掉到船外時
if they fall out of the boat that is taking them there.
拯救他們的性命。
This is not just a crisis, it's a test.
這不只是危機，更是種考驗。
It's a test that civilizations have faced down the ages.
這是文明面臨的長期考驗，
It's a test of our humanity.
對人性的考驗。
It's a test of us in the Western world
這要考驗在西方世界的我們，
of who we are and what we stand for.
我們是誰，還有我們為何而戰。
It's a test of our character, not just our policies.
這在考驗我們的人格， 而不僅是政策。
And refugees are a hard case.
而難民問題是個艱難的例子。
They do come from faraway parts of the world.
他們的確來自世界偏遠之地、
They have been through trauma.
曾受過創傷，
They're often of a different religion.
通常和我們擁有不同信仰，
Those are precisely the reasons we should be helping refugees,
這正是我們應該幫助難民的原因，
not a reason not to help them.
而非不幫助他們的原因。
And it's a reason to help them because of what it says about us.
我們要幫助難民， 因為這會顯出我們是怎樣的人。
It's revealing of our values.
那透露出我們的價值觀。
Empathy and altruism are two of the foundations of civilization.
同理及利他主義是文明的兩座基石。
Turn that empathy and altruism into action
把同理心和利他主義化為行動，
and we live out a basic moral credo.
並活出基本道德信條。
And in the modern world, we have no excuse.
在當代世界，我們責無旁貸。
We can't say we don't know what's happening in Juba, South Sudan,
我們不能說自己不知道 南蘇丹的朱巴
or Aleppo, Syria.
或敘利亞的阿勒坡發生什麼事。
It's there, in our smartphone
這些新聞就在我們的手機裡，
in our hand.
在我們的手中。
Ignorance is no excuse at all.
無知不再是藉口。
Fail to help, and we show we have no moral compass at all.
冷眼旁觀顯示出 我們完全沒有道德感。
It's also revealing about whether we know our own history.
這也透露出我們是否了解自身歷史。
The reason that refugees have rights around the world
難民在這個世界有人權，
is because of extraordinary Western leadership
是因為西方卓越的領導力，
by statesmen and women after the Second World War
二戰後由政治家主導，
that became universal rights.
因而成為普世權利。
Trash the protections of refugees, and we trash our own history.
踐踏保護難民權利 就等於踐踏自己的歷史。
This is --
這也……
(Applause)
（掌聲）
This is also revealing about the power of democracy
這也顯示出民主的力量，
as a refuge from dictatorship.
作為一種逃離獨裁的手段。
How many politicians have you heard say,
你們聽過多少政客說過：
"We believe in the power of our example, not the example of our power."
「我們相信典範的力量， 而非力量的示範」？
What they mean is what we stand for is more important than the bombs we drop.
意思是為何而戰比丟炸彈還重要。
Refugees seeking sanctuary
尋求聖所的難民
have seen the West as a source of hope and a place of haven.
知道西方是希望的來源和避難所。
Russians, Iranians,
俄國人、伊朗人、
Chinese, Eritreans, Cubans,
中國人、厄利垂亞人和古巴人
they've come to the West for safety.
都來西方尋求安全居所。
We throw that away at our peril.
我們冒著風險丟開他們。
And there's one other thing it reveals about us:
而這透露出一件事情：
whether we have any humility for our own mistakes.
我們是否虛心看待自己犯的錯誤。
I'm not one of these people
我和某些人不同，
who believes that all the problems in the world are caused by the West.
那些人相信世上所有問題 都由西方世界造成。
They're not.
不是這樣的。
But when we make mistakes, we should recognize it.
但如果我們犯錯了，就應該察覺到。
It's not an accident that the country which has taken
某國家接收比其他國家更多的難民，
more refugees than any other, the United States,
這不是巧合，例如美國
has taken more refugees from Vietnam than any other country.
比其他國家接收更多越南難民。
It speaks to the history.
它講述著歷史。
But there's more recent history, in Iraq and Afghanistan.
但伊拉克和阿富汗還有更近的歷史。
You can't make up for foreign policy errors
你無法藉由人道行動
by humanitarian action,
彌補外交政策的失誤。
but when you break something, you have a duty to try to help repair it,
但如果你毀壞某樣事物， 就有責任修好它。
and that's our duty now.
而這正是我們現在的責任。
Do you remember at the beginning of the talk,
你記得在這場演講的開始，
I said I wanted to explain that the refugee crisis
我說想解釋難民危機
was manageable, not insoluble?
可以解決，而非無計可施嗎？
That's true. I want you to think in a new way,
這是真的， 你們可以換個方式想想，
but I also want you to do things.
但我也希望你們做些什麼。
If you're an employer,
如果你是雇主，
hire refugees.
雇用難民吧。
If you're persuaded by the arguments,
若你被這些論點說服了，
take on the myths
起來打破這些迷思吧，
when family or friends or workmates repeat them.
尤其當家人朋友或同事再次提起時。
If you've got money, give it to charities
如果你有錢，
If you're a citizen,
如果你是個公民，
vote for politicians
投票給會實踐以上解決方案的
(Applause)
（掌聲）
The duty to strangers
我們對陌生人的責任
shows itself
顯露在
in small ways and big,
大大小小的地方，
prosaic and heroic.
以平凡或非凡的方式出現。
In 1942,
1942 年，
my aunt and my grandmother were living in Brussels
我阿姨和祖母住在布魯塞爾，
under German occupation.
當時在德國統治之下。
They received a summons
他們接到納粹當局的命令，
My grandmother immediately thought something was amiss.
祖母立刻察覺事有蹊蹺。
She pleaded with her relatives
她求她的親戚
not to go to Brussels Railway Station.
不要去火車站。
Her relatives said to her,
親戚們告訴她：
"If we don't go, if we don't do what we're told,
「如果我們不去，不遵照命令，
then we're going to be in trouble."
就會惹禍上身。」
You can guess what happened
你們可以猜到去車站的親戚們
to the relatives who went to Brussels Railway Station.
後來怎麼了。
They were never seen again.
從此再也沒人見過他們。
But my grandmother and my aunt,
但我的祖母和阿姨
they went to a small village
到了一座小村莊，
south of Brussels
在布魯塞爾的南邊，
where they'd been on holiday in the decade before,
在那之前是她們的度假場所。
and they presented themselves at the house of the local farmer,
她們到一個當地農夫的家裡，
a Catholic farmer called Monsieur Maurice,
一個叫莫瑞斯的天主教農夫。
and they asked him to take them in.
她們求他收留，
And he did,
他答應了。
and by the end of the war,
而在戰爭結束前
17 Jews, I was told, were living in that village.
有 17 名猶太人住在那村莊。
And when I was teenager, I asked my aunt,
我年輕時問過阿姨：
"Can you take me to meet Monsieur Maurice?"
「你可以帶我去看莫瑞斯先生嗎？」
And she said, "Yeah, I can. He's still alive. Let's go and see him."
她說：「可以啊， 他還活著，我們去看他吧。」
And so, it must have been '83, '84,
所以大概在 1983 或 1984 年
we went to see him.
我們去拜訪他。
And I suppose, like only a teenager could,
我猜想，就像青少年想得到的那樣，
when I met him,
當我見到他時，
he was this white-haired gentleman,
他是名頭髮灰白的紳士。
I said to him,
我問他：
"Why did you do it?
「你為什麼要這麼做？
Why did you take that risk?"
為什麼要冒這個險？」
And he looked at me and he shrugged,
他看著我，聳聳肩，
and he said, in French,
然後用法語回答：
"On doit."
「On doit.」
"One must."
「我必須。」
It was innate in him.
這是他與生俱來的特質，
It was natural.
是再自然不過的決定。
And my point to you is it should be natural and innate in us, too.
我的意思是，這對我們 也該是自然而然的決定。
Tell yourself,
告訴你自己，
this refugee crisis is manageable,
難民危機是可解決的，
not unsolvable,
而非無計可施。
and each one of us
我們當中的每個人
has a personal responsibility to help make it so.
都有各自的責任要付諸實踐，
Because this is about the rescue of us and our values
因為這關乎挽救我們自身的價值觀，
as well as the rescue of refugees and their lives.
以及拯救難民的生命。
Thank you very much indeed.
真的很謝謝你們。
(Applause)
（掌聲）
Bruno Giussani: David, thank you. David Miliband: Thank you.
布魯諾：大衛，謝謝你。 大衛：謝謝。
BG: Those are strong suggestions
布魯諾：這些都是很有力的建議，
and your call for individual responsibility is very strong as well,
你對個人責任的呼籲也很有力。
you mentioned, and these are your words, "extraordinary Western leadership"
你剛提到「西方非凡的領導」
which led 60-something years ago
在六十幾年前主導
to the whole discussion about human rights,
關於人權的討論、
to the conventions on refugees, etc. etc.
主導了難民會議等等。
That leadership happened after a big trauma
這領導權發生在 一個重大的創傷之後，
and happened in a consensual political space,
發生在雙方同意成立的政治空間。
and now we are in a divisive political space.
如今我們處在一個分歧的政治空間。
Actually, refugees have become one of the divisive issues.
事實上，難民本身成為分歧的議題，
So where will leadership come from today?
所以現今的領導權從何而來呢？
DM: Well, I think that you're right to say
大衛：嗯，我想你說得沒錯，
that the leadership forged in war
也就是在戰時形成的領導權，
has a different temper and a different tempo
擁有不同的性情及節奏、
and a different outlook
不同觀點，
than leadership forged in peace.
有別於和平時期形成的領導權。
And so my answer would be the leadership has got to come from below,
所以我的回答是， 領導權必須來自下層，
not from above.
而非來自上層。
I mean, a recurring theme of the conference this week
就像這週不斷出現的會議主題
has been about the democratization of power.
都是關於民主化的力量。
And we've got to preserve our own democracies,
我們必須保存我們的民主，
but we've got to also activate our own democracies.
但也必須活化民主。
And when people say to me,
當人們告訴我：
"There's a backlash against refugees,"
「有人強烈反對難民」，
what I say to them is,
我告訴他們：
"No, there's a polarization,
「不對，其實有兩極的聲音，
and at the moment,
而此刻
those who are fearful are making more noise
害怕的人
And so my answer to your question is that we will sponsor and encourage
所以我的回答是， 我們要付出資助及鼓勵，
and give confidence to leadership
並在我們總動員時
when we mobilize ourselves.
對領導者有信心。
And I think that when you are in a position of looking for leadership,
我覺得如果你想要成為領導者，
you have to look inside
就必須看得更深，
and mobilize in your own community
並在自己的社群動員，
to try to create conditions for a different kind of settlement.
好創造出不同種安置的居住條件。
BG: Thank you, David. Thanks for coming to TED.
布魯諾：大衛，謝謝你來 TED。
(Applause)
（掌聲）